Guide to the Herbert Silvette Papers, circa 1936-1988
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Herbert Silvette papers circa 1936-1988
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Silvette, Herbert, 1906-
2.5 Linear Feet Approx. 900 Items
Author, and physiologist and pharmacologist at the University of Virginia Medical School.
Collection comprises material relating to and examples of Herbert Silvette's writings, which include short stories, novels, and his work on the English translator Philemon Holland (1552-1637). There is also a large body of correspondence from Archibald MacLeish, which Silvette compiled in The Stiletto Letters. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Herbert Silvette Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2011.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises material relating to and examples of Herbert Silvette's writings, which include short stories, novels, and his work on the English translator Philemon Holland (1552-1637). There is also a large body of correspondence from Archibald MacLeish, which Silvette compiled in The Stiletto Letters.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Silvette, Herbert, 1906-
Holland, Philemon, 1552-1637
MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982
Medicine in literature -- United States
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Archibald MacLeish Correspondence Series, 1950-1973, (2 boxes)
  Contains correspondence between Silvette and Archibald MacLeish, who addressed Silvette as Stiletto in his letters. MacLeish (1892-1982) was an American poet, playwright, teacher and public official, and served as Librarian of Congress from 1939 to 1944 and as Assistant Secretary of State from 1944 to 1945. Silvette compiled these letters in a volume entitled The Stiletto Letters.
  - Correspondence from MacLeish, 1950-1973, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - The Stiletto Letters: Correspondence from Daniel Thomas Rolfe, 1950-1964 (Box 1)
  - The Stiletto Letters: loose leaf typescript, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - The Stiletto Letters: related material (Box 1)
  - Volume: The Stiletto Letters, typescript, 1950-1976 (Box 6)
- Philemon Holland Materials Series, 1936-1954 and undated, (4 boxes)
  Contains research materials and writings relating to Silvette's unpublished study of Philemon Holland. Holland (1552-1637) was an English translator best know for his translation of Pliny the Elder's Natural History.
  - Bibliographical notes on a speech by Holland, undated (Box 2)
  - Holland biography: correspondence, notes, reprints, photos, drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - Holland related material: correspondence, notes, and miscellaneous printed material, undated (Box 2)
  - Holland related material: notes on 5x8 index cards, undated (Box 2)
  - Holland related material: photostats and mounted prints, undated (Box 2)
  - Holland related material: prints and negatives, undated (Box 2)
  - Interpres: the Life and Times of Philemon Holland of Coventry, Doctor of Physicke, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2-3)
  - Quotations used for Holland biography, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Interpres: the Life and Times of Philemon Holland of Coventry, Doctor of Physicke, typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, circa 1936-1954 and undated, (5 volumes) (Box 5)
  - A Short-title List of the Writings of Philemon Holland of Coventry, Doctor of Physicke, 1939 (Box 5)
    Privately printed for Silvette at the University of Virginia Press by John S. Peters. Contains extensive manuscript notes throughout.
- Writings Series, 1960-1985 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Contains several short stories and novels written by Silvette as well as his semi-autobiographical novel A Chapter of Chances. Most of the short stories deal with medical or scientific themes. Silvette also wrote under the pseudonym Dogbolt Barnaby.
  - An Affair of Honor, undated (Box 2)
  - A Chapter of Chances, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3-4)
  - Luduvico, undated (Box 4)
  - Lydwardine, undated (Box 4)
  - Professor Bubble's Experiment, undated, (2 copies) (Box 4)
  - The Coachman is Dead, typescript, 1960-1985 (Box 7)
  - Day of Judgment, typescript, undated (Box 7)